Part Two: Your Nutrition Support Team
You are not alone in your treatment
and nutrition goals.
In addition to your doctor and their team,
from the beginning
to the end of your treatment,
you will have the support
of our department's dedicated dietitian
and speech Therapy team.
Our dietitian will provide guidance
and give general advice
about what to eat
and how to get more calories in.
Any questions you may have about nutrition
or your diet can be addressed to them.
Be sure to see the dietitian every week
during your treatment.
In addition to our dedicated dietitian,
we have a group of speech
and language therapists.
Their job is to make sure you are
swallowing well so you can eat and drink.
To do this, they will
have you complete a series
of tests
and perform strengthening exercises.
One test is the modified barium swallow study,
which is usually done
two months after finishing radiation.
Unless you are at a higher
risk of choking,
also known as aspiration.
The team will
have you drink a liquid containing a dye
that will allow them to see your
swallowing function using X-ray imaging.
Specifically,
they are verifying that the liquid
is going down the proper pathway:
The esophagus.
Food or liquid incorrectly entering
the airway is called aspiration
and is something that we want to avoid.
In addition to these tests,
the speech therapy team will also teach
you exercises to engage
and strengthen your chewing, swallowing,
and speaking muscles.
Much like exercising the body at the gym,
these exercises maintain good,
healthy function of these muscles
so you can continue to eat and drink well.